I'll see you next time.
At the end of our gathering, there's tables in the back, so if you missed that on your
way in and you want to participate, feel free to take a bathroom trip or, you know, multitask
on a real bathroom trip.
Either way, we'll give you time at the end, but I wanted to let you know that.
Hey, in classic Canvas fashion, we are breaking, we are going against all church growth strategies,
and we're talking about money right after Easter Sunday, you know?
It's like, hey, welcome all you new people.
Let's tell you about how awesome Jesus is.
Now let's talk about the thing that everybody hates to talk about in church.
And I know that the church has gotten a bad rap for how we've talked about money, and I personally
as a pastor have avoided doing this for as long as I have been a pastor.
I have typically not really looked forward to something like this.
We have never talked about money as a church.
We're only three years old, so, you know, it was inevitable at some point.
But I'm actually looking forward to this for the first time in a long time because what
I've come to realize is that when we talk about money, we're actually not talking about money
at all.
We're actually talking about our hearts.
And how we spend and manage our money is actually one of the clearest revealers of what
is in our hearts, which is why Jesus actually talks about money, wealth, and possessions pretty
frequently.
If you read through the Gospels, you will realize that it is not a topic that he shies
away from.
And the reality, the reason that he does not shy away from it is not because that he needs
your money.
It's actually because he wants your heart.
And so one of the most famous sayings that we have from Jesus about money is you cannot
serve God and mammon.
There we go.
Some of y'all got your KJVs this morning.
Yes, mammon is this transliteration, right?
It's this word.
It literally, it means the thing you trust in.
And it's in the context of money and there's a reason it gets translated money.
But when we sang that song, You Have No Rival, and we sing it with boldness and we declare
it, I believe it and I think we all believe it.
But then we look to our financial situations, and the reality is oftentimes we put our trust
in that more than we put our trust in God, that God actually does have a rival, and one
of the clearest rivals that he has shows up in money.
So again, he doesn't talk about it because he needs it.
He didn't spend very much money when he was here.
He wasn't one of those private jet pastors.
And we are not talking about it because we need your money.
Our church is in a very healthy financial position, and so there's no, like, something
behind the curtain here.
I really, as a pastor, I want all of us to be more fully surrendered to Jesus, and so this
is just one of the things that we have to talk about at some point.
And so this series is going to end.
It's only three weeks.
Thank you.
You can thank me later.
Or you can thank me now.
It's fine.
Three-week series.
The third week is going to end with a three-day seminar, and the reality is our church is
very economically diverse, and so I couldn't give you practical wisdom from the stage that
would apply to all of your financial situations.
And so we've partnered with a ministry called Life Institute.
They are going to be coming in on the third week of the series and doing a three-day seminar
covering very specific topics around biblical stewardship in detail.
And the biggest thing that I'm most excited about is the whole time they're here, they're going
to be offering free one-on-one financial meetings where you can just sit down with them, share
a little bit about your financial position, and they will, as your brothers in Christ that
you will then never see again, and they will never come to me and tell me what they found
out about you and your money.
They will just give you some wisdom and some insight from their experience and knowledge.
You can find out all of the information about this seminar at our webpage, canvascommunity.church.money,
because we couldn't think of anything catchier than that that you would not remember.
So check all that out.
Make plans.
Talk to your spouses, your family.
Make plans to attend one of those sessions.
They're going to be here for passages that morning, service.
We're going to have a lunch.
You can stay and eat free food and learn more about finances, and there'll be a couple
sessions.
Prioritize those one-on-one meetings.
The reason I'm bringing them in, one of the reasons that I suggested to our board we do
this is because I actually, Marissa and I met with the guy who runs this ministry, and he
helped us tremendously.
We'd been through biblical stewardship things.
We were debt-free outside of our mortgage.
We mostly lived on a budget.
Anybody else?
Can you say you have a budget-ish?
Okay, we had a budget-ish.
And after one hour of meeting with this guy, he just really gave us some insights so that
we could plan more intentionally, which ultimately led us to be able to be freely generous with
spontaneous needs, which is something that we were never able to do in the past.
And so it's so fun.
I don't know, those of you that have had the opportunity to do this, when you have just like
a slush fund of generosity sitting there, and you have a need in front of you, and you
can just, without feeling guilt or fear or shame or anything, you can just be like,
here, I want to help you.
It's such a fun thing to do.
It is the abundant life.
And it would not have happened for me and Marissa if we didn't have somebody on the outside
poking holes at some of our budget practices.
So I highly recommend you check it out.
Plan on attending some of the sessions.
This is not a sermon.
This is a commercial for the seminar.
I will preach a sermon here in just a second.
Cool.
So that's where we're headed.
And for the next two weeks, the last week, we're going to get really specific and help
you contextually make decisions for yourself.
The next two weeks, we're going to zoom out and look at much bigger picture principles
and pitfalls of what happens, even if we do have resources available, even if we do steward
our money well.
There's really kind of two sides of the coin if you get to a point where you're in a decent
financial position, is you can over save, right?
You can be like, oh, I finally got money coming in.
I need to provide, protect, build up.
And you can over save and you can also over spend.
And typically those two people marry each other and then there's conflict.
And so we're going to talk a little bit about what that looks like and how do we kind of
navigate that.
There's a podcast that I'd like to recommend to you.
Again, this is still a commercial.
I will get to the sermon, a podcast from the Bible project that's in your bulletins.
It's going to be in the newsletter.
And it's two guys that met at Harvard Business School, both committed Christians, both had
been taught that, you know, you tithe because you're a Christian and then everything else
is yours and you can do whatever you want with it.
One of them was very into spending.
One of them was very into saving and they just shared their story of what God did in their
hearts at business, at Harvard Business School of all places.
I'd love for you to check that out.
Okay.
That's three weeks commercial.
You good?
We should pray and then we should read the Bible.
Father in heaven, Jehovah Jireh, the Lord who sees us.
And who provides what we need at the right time.
I'm sure there are many of us in the room, God, who are anxious about our financial position
and the thought that we're going to be talking about that in church is increasing that anxiety.
I pray by your Holy Spirit, God, that you would just relieve that.
That you would help each individual in the room, wherever they are in their financial position,
to know that you are the God who sees them, provides for them, and who wants their heart.
And so God, whatever you need to reveal to me and my heart and my idolatry and trust issues
and whatever you need to reveal to all of us and whatever just like encouragement and freedom
you need to give us, God, I pray by your Holy Spirit, you would do that as we read your Scriptures
today.
And God, that this would just be something that bears fruit over our lives and in our church
so that we can not just pray, give us this day our daily bread, God, but that we can be
the embodiment of that prayer to those around us.
For your glory, for our good, and for the good of our neighbors.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
We're going to be in Luke chapter 12.
If you want to follow along with me in the Bible this morning.
I'd love to, a little bit, I'm trying to increase this crowd participation thing.
I don't know why.
It just feels like something cool that I should do so that you guys don't like fall asleep
10 minutes into the sermon.
So I'd love it if you just yell out something cool that you wanted to be when you grew up
when you were a kid.
Boxer.
That's, that's cool.
Anybody got, anybody top boxer?
Race car driver.
Astronaut's pretty cool.
NASCAR or something else?
NASCAR.
All right, NASCAR.
Anybody else got something cooler than that?
Indiana Jones.
Indiana Jones, a rancher.
Okay, we've got some cool stuff in the room.
Embarrassing for me because what's going to happen here is I'm going to tell you that my
mom probably still has a book in our house that I made her buy on how to become a mime.
I should have asked her before this to bring it because I'm sure she has it.
I did go through a phase where I want it to be a mime.
See it.
It's too rusty.
But thankfully, thankfully for me, the mime phase progressed to a magic phase, which is
a little bit cooler.
A little bit cooler.
And any of you that have really seen or witnessed like good magic, you know that magicians capture
our attention by making us feel like we see something that isn't actually there.
Or we miss something that's right in front of us.
And the crazy part is that we know it's happening and it still works.
The best illusions actually don't trick our eyes, but they play on our assumptions about
reality.
They play on what we think we see and our eyes fill in the gaps about things that aren't
actually there.
That's why I personally, I love watching magicians like expose other magicians, right?
It's like, let me show you how he did this or she did this or let me show you what.
And then like, as soon as you see it, you're like, how did I not see that?
Well, you didn't see it because they're, they're, they're masters at manipulating what you assume
to be true about reality.
And as we open up our Bibles to Luke chapter 12, I think that's what, what Jesus is going
to begin to do for us is he's going to begin to expose some things that we believe to be
true about reality that actually aren't.
He's going to show us ways in which we are kind of believing an illusion about what is true
about reality and what resources are available and, and, and what we have to do to be provided
for, and he's going to offer an alternative way of viewing reality.
And it's all kind of building off what we've talked about in the series on Ephesians and
in our sermon on Easter, because he's going to say, there's this old way of looking at reality.
There's this kingdom of the world way of looking at reality, and that's going to impact the
way you view your resources and the way that you use your resources.
It is manipulated by the powers and principalities, and it is fueled by this, um, kind of getting
kicked out of the garden reality where there's sweat on our brow.
And we just feel like there's not enough resources and we have to provide for ourself.
And he's going to say, there's actually this alternative way of viewing the world in the
kingdom of God, that you have a father who's pleased to provide for you.
And there's more than enough resources for you and everyone around you.
But, but that reality is, is kind of a behind the curtain, above the clouds type of reality
that we need someone to expose the lie that we're believing, the deception that we are
being deceived by.
Does that make sense?
All right.
So let's just read it.
Um, and, and hopefully I can not get lost.
All right.
Luke 12, starting in verse 13, Jesus is like got a big crowd.
It's one of the biggest crowds he's had at this point in Luke, and he is preaching about
the kingdom and about your relationship with God.
And in verse 13, it says, someone in the crowd said to him, teacher, tell my brother to divide
the inheritance with me.
But he said to him, man, who made me a judge or an arbitrator over you?
And he said to them, so he has the conversation with the individual and then he zooms out to
the group, take care and be on your guard against all covetousness, which is a word we all use every day.
I had to practice pronouncing that in the mirror a couple of times.
For one's life does not consist in the abundance of possessions.
So immediately we have somebody breaking into a sermon from Jesus in front of a huge crowd about
the kingdom and about eternal matters.
And he says, excuse me, sir, can you tell my brother to divide the inheritance?
You can see where his mindset is, where his focus is.
He's at church listening to a sermon from the Son of God.
And he's thinking about money, resources.
It would be like one of you in the middle of like, I get to the climactic point of my sermon.
I'm preaching the gospel to people who don't yet know Jesus.
And somebody in the back stands up and says, Ryan, can you tell my wife to cool it on the
Lululemon leggings?
Right?
It's like, what are we doing here?
We're doing something.
We're talking about something far greater than this reality.
And the question that this guy has, I use the Lululemon illustration because the question
that this guy has comes from a place of privilege.
The fact that his father was a landowner makes him like already far wealthier than like a majority
of the crowd that Jesus is talking to.
Jesus himself being a poor, like homeless, itinerant preacher.
And this guy who's probably one of the richer guys in the crowd is like, hey, let's talk about
my problem.
Well, my brother has my stuff and I want to get it back.
And I think the reality is there's probably some, there's probably some injustice there.
Like the brother's probably keeping some things that are rightfully his.
And he knows that Jesus is about justice.
So he's like, this is my opportunity.
I got one shot, right?
This guy's going to, he's going to make it right.
But I think this is one of the reasons that Jesus doesn't get lost in the specifics of the
situation because he knows it's already from a place of privilege.
And so what he does instead of dealing with the situations, he launches into teaching on greed.
Because the brother is valuing the accumulation of more stuff above his relationship with his brother.
And Jesus wants to expose what's happening in our hearts.
And what this shows about how we view the world.
Christ's main point that he states from the very beginning is be careful not to become greedy because life does not consist in the accumulation of things.
I heard one pastor say it this way this week, having a lot does not mean that you have a life.
And so this is where Jesus is saying, hey, like, it's not a totally ignoring your situation.
He's just saying, this is revealing.
I want to show you what this says about what's true in your heart.
And he goes on in classic Jesus fashion to tell an awesome story that's going to really make his point.
In verse 16, he says, and he told them a parable saying, the land of a rich man.
Everybody say rich man.
The land of a rich man produced plentiful.
And he thought to himself, what shall I do?
For I have nowhere to store my crops.
And he said, I will do this.
I'll tear down my barns and I'll build larger ones.
And then I'll store all my grain and my goods.
And I will say to my soul, love that he's having an internal dialogue with his soul.
Soul, you have ample goods laid up for many years.
Relax, eat, drink, and be merry.
But God said to him, fool, this night, your soul.
Those are required of you.
And the things you have prepared, whose will they be?
So this is the one who lays up a treasure for himself and is not rich towards God.
So Jesus tells the story of a man who's already rich,
trying to decide what he's going to do with the additional resources that his land has produced for him.
And we say his land has produced for him.
But if we know the economic system of the world, we actually know that it's like day workers and tenant farmers who are barely feeding themselves and their family,
who are the ones who gathered this crop for this rich man.
And they are mostly the people that are filling the audience of Jesus.
And so when Jesus begins to tell the story, the people are probably thinking, hey, I know what he can do with the excess grain that he has.
Right?
He can give it to those that the sweat of their brow produced the profit that he is trying to figure out what to do with.
He's surrounded by people in need and the internal dialogue that he's having is what am I going to do with this stuff and how is it going to lead to my security and my joy?
And Jesus is exposing this illusion about what life and reality is like by telling this story.
And before you get on your high horse and before I get on my high horse, it's April.
Some of you got some tax return money from the government this past month or two.
And I would just ask you to consider to yourself, what did your internal dialogue look like when you got a check that wasn't expected or bigger than it was expected?
What does our internal dialogue say about what we believe about our resources and the world around us?
And the reality is when we read this story and we hear a rich man got more stuff than he needed, every one of us in the room thought about the person one tax bracket above us.
Because all of us, no matter where God has blessed us with, no matter what resource, no matter where we're at in the totem pole, it's always the group above us that needs to hear the message about generosity.
And I myself have struggled with this for a long time.
I was a youth pastor.
My wife was working part-time at a bank.
And we had more than enough.
But I was just, I was looking at the person that now makes what I make.
And I'm like, man, they need to hear a message about generosity.
And now that I'm where I'm at, I'm looking at one step up the ladder.
They need to hear a message about generosity.
And Jesus is just tearing this all down.
He's saying, it's not about how much, it's about the view of the world that you have.
Because conversations about money aren't ultimately about money.
They're about what we love and we put our trust in.
And this man's internal dialogue reveals the way that he views the world.
It is a scarcity mindset.
There is a limited amount of resources and life is short.
So I'm going to store up as much as I can so that I can sit back and relax and have peace and joy.
This is the mindset of the kingdom of this world.
Resources are limited and life is short.
And so therefore, it impacts the way that we view the resources around us.
And Jesus makes a clear hyperlink to the story of Ecclesiastes and the Jewish Scriptures.
And if you grew up in the Bible, you know that, or if you grew up in church, you probably know that story.
But for those of you that don't, Solomon wrote the book of Ecclesiastes.
He was one of the most wealthy and successful kings in all of the nation of Israel.
And he launched, just for fun, because he was bored, launched an experiment where he was going to try and find the value of life.
He was going to use all of his resources, all of his wealth, all of his wisdom.
And he was going to figure out where life could be found.
And this eat, drink, and be merry phrase is something that he coined, because what he figured out is no matter what he put his money, his time, his wisdom to, it was all futile and vanity.
It was like striving after the wind.
His conclusion is that life under the sun is vanity.
The illusion of scarcity is the worldview of a life under the sun.
The whole point of the book of Ecclesiastes is there's actually more to life than what's under the sun.
And Jesus is setting this whole worldview up in his parable because he wants us to realize that there is a worldview that we are believing under the sun, that life is short, and that resources are limited.
And therefore, it impacts what we do with them.
Not only that, but life is but a vapor is another thing that Solomon talks about in Ecclesiastes, which gets to the point of the story.
It's like, hey, you think that you have this long future ahead of you, but you never know how long you are going to live.
That should impact the way that we view our resources.
There is a crafty illusion going on under the sun that causes us to think that there are limited resources for a temporary life,
and that true joy and peace is found in accumulating more things, and Jesus is exposing the lie.
And the reality is, in church this morning, most of us are aware that this is a lie.
Most of us would agree with that statement that just because you have a lot, you don't have a life.
But if someone sat down and took a hard look at how you spend your money, at how I spend my money,
would our lives reflect that we believe that reality, or would our finances look more like this under the sun reality?
Jesus says that true life is found in being rich towards God, loving the Lord your God with all of your heart, soul, mind, and strength,
and loving your neighbor as yourself.
Is anybody having fun yet?
Okay, good.
Jesus says that true life is found in loving God and loving others, and over the next few weeks,
I hope that we will double-click just for a couple weeks on our financial decisions
and consider what that reveals to us about the worldview that we have.
Are we living with this under-the-sun mentality that leads us to believe the illusion of scarcity?
And here's a bonus application.
Sometimes I write things in my notes that's, like, bonus, it's if I have time to get to them.
And usually, even if I don't have time to get to them, I do them anyway.
That's why we're here later than we should be.
So, do you guys want to hear the bonus application, or do you want me to keep going?
Okay.
See, you guys are great.
This is why I do it.
I don't even, I usually don't even tell you.
You guys are getting invited into my internal dialogue.
You're welcome.
So, if you're familiar with the story of Ecclesiastes, you'll know that Solomon even complains about the idea of leaving an inheritance to his kids.
He's, like, super wealthy and wise, and he looks at his kids who are acting a fool, and he's like,
I worked so hard.
I have all this stuff.
And when I die, it's got to go to those knuckleheads.
And when we input that story into this story, I can't help but think, what would the father who worked hard to provide an inheritance for his children be thinking about the fact that his kids are at odds with one another, fighting over the limited resources that he left them?
And that message really hits me hard as a father who feels the pressure to provide for my son, who wants him not to have to worry about food and things like that.
The question for me becomes, would I rather leave Rory a bigger inheritance, or would I rather demonstrate for him the reality that true life is not found in the accumulation of possessions, but in generosity to those around us?
And do I want my son to get a bunch of stuff that he doesn't know how to use in the way that God would want him to use it, or do I want to invite him into the process of using our money the way that God would want us to use it?
And is that leading him to true life, or is me just giving him a pile of stuff at the end of my life leading him to true life?
It'd be a small pile, but it could still be a pile.
And I'm already starting this, and it's an invitation, and it's a process.
He got some money for his birthday, and I told him, I said, buddy, you know, when mommy and daddy get money, we take a little bit aside, and we use it to help others who don't have money.
Is that something that you would like to do?
And he said, no.
And I said, okay, we'll get there.
It's all right.
I'm not going to force you to do something.
Like, we'll get there.
We'll figure that out later.
But the question becomes, like, again, it's not a conversation about money.
It's a conversation about our hearts.
And so Jesus directly addresses the greed that comes from this scarcity mindset.
But he doesn't stay on the topic of greed.
He actually moves on to the topic of anxiety in verse 22.
And he said to his disciples, therefore, I tell you, do not be anxious about your life, what you will eat, nor about your body.
What you will put on for life is more than food, and the body is more than clothing.
So he addresses this wealthy landowner, younger son, and he says, look, dude, like, your issue is probably greed.
Probably greed.
I don't need to be the Son of God to tell you that you're greedy.
And then he looks at his disciples, who I don't think greed is an issue for the disciples.
They have given up pretty much everything they have to follow a, like, homeless, itinerant rabbi.
But he looks to his disciples, and he pinpoints something that their view of money reveals about their heart, and that is anxiety.
His disciples have sold most of what they have to follow a homeless, itinerant rabbi.
Greed isn't likely their heart posture, but anxiety might be.
And for many of us in the room, this is likely the primary emotion we feel when the topic of money comes up.
The sermon bumper started rolling, and anxiety probably rose in the room for some of you.
There is this scarcity illusion that has us anxious that we won't be able to keep up with our bills or provide for our kids what their peers have.
We don't want to talk about or even think about money.
We'd rather ignore the topic altogether.
And the reality is that this scarcity illusion, I want to be contextual and understand here that this illusion that we're talking about, that Jesus is exposing, it is an illusion.
But when enough people believe it, it becomes reality.
And many people in the crowd and many people in the room are anxious for food and clothes because they work for people like the rich man in the parable.
And the economy in the first century is not that much different than the economy here where it's hard to get rich, but once you're there, it's really easy to get richer.
And it's really hard for those below them to get above where they're at.
And many of us feel somewhat trapped in our economic class because our system makes it easier for the rich to get richer and the poor to stay where they are.
So I don't want to act like that isn't a reality that might cause anxiety in many of our hearts.
And in Luke, when Jesus first announces the kingdom of God, in Luke chapter 4, he gets baptized, he goes into the wilderness for the temptation.
And his first declaration of what he came to preach, the kingdom of God, in Luke, he says that the kingdom of God is good news to the poor.
And the time of the Lord's favor has come.
And so, yes, this is an illusion that has become a reality.
But what Jesus is inviting us into is to reject the view of scarcity in the kingdom of under the sun.
And he's inviting us to embrace the view of abundance in the kingdom of God.
And the only way that the gospel becomes good news to the poor is that when those of us who have resources realize that we have more than we need and that we're invited to share with others,
that's when we start to break the lie of the enemy, of the powers and principalities that have us kind of under the sun reality.
We're locked in and we're lost in it.
And we're invited to lay that lie down and to use our abundance to help those around us.
That's when the kingdom of God becomes good news to the poor.
Amen.
And even though we really can't blame the anxious people about their anxiety, Jesus doesn't let them off the hook.
He wants them also.
He wants the greedy and the anxious to get their eyes above the sun, above this earthly kingdom reality to the kingdom of God.
He tells this story.
For life is more than food.
The body is more than clothing.
Consider the ravens.
They neither sow nor reap.
They have no storehouses or barns and yet God feeds them.
How much more value are you than the birds?
And which of you by being anxious can add a single hour to your lifespan?
If then you are not able to do a small thing like that, why are you anxious about the rest?
Consider the lilies, how they grow.
They neither toil nor spin.
Yet I tell you, even Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like one of these.
But it is God.
But if God so clothes the grass which is alive in the field today and tomorrow is thrown in the oven, how much more will he clothe you, O you of little faith?
Do not seek what you are to eat or what you are to drink, nor be worried.
For all the nations of the world seek after these things.
Your Father knows you need them.
Instead, seek his kingdom and these things will be added to you.
So Jesus kind of demonstrates, shares this illusion that we're all believing and holding on to, that there's limited resources and that life is short.
And he's inviting us to see that there is a God who is a God of abundance, who provides for the birds of the air and the flowers of the ground.
And if this is the God who created everything and who made you in his image, then there is not just abundance for the flowers and the birds, but there is an abundance for you.
And we have to begin to lift our eyes above the worldly principalities and powers, the illusion of scarcity and temporary life.
And we have to believe that we were created not just for life here now, but for eternity.
And that there is more than enough because God is the God who made everything.
This is the truest way of seeing God's world as it is in heaven.
It confronts both the greedy rich and the anxious poor.
None of us are off the hook in this conversation.
And it ultimately isn't a conversation about money, but about the way we see the world and the way we relate to one another.
Greed and worry are two ways of living inside the same illusion.
And Jesus says, look at the birds and look at the flowers.
They don't store food.
They aren't anxious about what to wear.
And yet their heavenly father clothes them and feeds them.
Verse 30 and 31 just directly confronts this two kingdom mindset.
He said, all the nations of the world, they all worry about where their food is going to come from.
But you, if you have embraced the reality of the kingdom of God, you don't have to worry about these things.
If you seek first his kingdom, all of these things will be added to you.
And just to keep our theme from Ephesians and Genesis, I threw up a slide here that I think is really helpful to understand what Jesus is doing.
I think, do I have it?
There it is.
I came to your side.
Yes, I did it.
We've been looking at these two realities of the world, the temporary reality of life under the sun.
And it is animated by the sweat of the brow, the anxiety that there won't be enough and that I have to provide for me and mine.
And that makes everybody that is not me and mine my enemy.
And in competition for a limited amount of resources, it says that life is temporary, that resources are limited, and it leads to greed or fear.
But thanks be to God for the cross, the empty tomb, the resurrection, and the ascension, inviting us into a new way of viewing reality that is good news for the poor, that life is not temporary but eternal, that resources are not limited but abundant.
And that leads us to live with generous, open hands that lead to true and abundant life.
This is what Jesus is trying to do here in this story.
The old humanity, the kingdom of this world, believes the lie of the enemy.
And we just grab more stuff and squeeze as much temporary enjoyment as we can out of our short lives.
And the invitation from Jesus is to embrace the kingdom of heaven, here and now, to realize life is eternal.
And in God's redeemed world, there is more than enough for everyone.
We can begin to live towards this reality even before we see it fully because it leads to true and abundant life.
My main point for this message this morning is that the illusion of scarcity produces greed and fear, and the abundance of God's kingdom produces generosity and joy.
Peace and joy come from living with an open hands towards other, and you don't have to have a lot to start living into this kingdom.
You don't even have to have financial resources to start being generous with your time and your energy and your prayers and your thoughts.
You can begin to live with open hands.
You don't have to be anxious.
Even if you don't have everything, when we pray, God gave us this prayer.
Give us this day our daily bread.
He gave that prayer to people that literally didn't know where their meal was going to come from the next day.
He's saying, trust me, pray to me, believe in me.
We can live in this reality here and now.
And then he lands the plane as Jesus often does with just a killer one-liner.
He says, fear not, little flock, for it is your father's good pleasure to give you the kingdom.
He says, don't be afraid.
He refers to the crowd like sheep.
They know this imagery well, that God is like a good shepherd who leads us beside still waters, who provides for our needs.
It's an allusion in my mind to John chapter 10 where it says the thief, the enemy, the powers and principalities who are trying to convince you to believe that your life is short and that resources are limited.
The purpose of the enemy is to steal, kill, and destroy.
But Jesus says, I have come to give you life and life more abundantly.
I am the good shepherd and the sheep hear my voice and they follow me.
The question becomes, whose voice are we listening to?
What view of reality are we believing?
It is your father's good pleasure to give you the kingdom.
And for those of us that grew up in the church, you might have kind of gotten a message that God's this angry God up in the sky who like is giving you stuff that he really doesn't want to give you.
And that is not the biblical view of God at all.
The biblical view of God is a God who is eager and excited.
It is his good pleasure to give you the kingdom.
You don't have to earn it.
You don't have to strive for it.
You don't have to store it up.
It is a gift that is freely given.
Our passage opened.
I have to talk to you guys about the aha moments in sermon prep when you are like, sorry, I already got a little anxiety about preaching a message on money.
Like I really want people to see Jesus clearly and beautifully in the midst of talking about money.
Because again, we are not talking about money.
We are talking about the heart.
And I had this aha moment like Wednesday afternoon that the passage we read today, it starts with the younger brother asking a question triggered by the firstborn son selfishly hoarding the limited inheritance of his earthly father.
And it ends with the one true firstborn son, sacrificially and generously distributing unlimited inheritance of an eternal father for all those who would receive it.
We have these two kingdoms just put in juxtaposition with one another.
The temporary earthly kingdom, the sons fighting over the resources, the older brother, the firstborn son keeping from his younger brother.
And then we have the gospel, which is the one true firstborn son, that God sent his one and only son who would sacrificially lay down his life to distribute the abundance of an eternal God to those of us who would receive it by faith.
This is the gospel.
This is God's grace.
This leads to a view of the world from an abundance perspective.
It invites us to live with open hands and it makes the gospel good news to the poor.
But we have to see it.
We have to believe it and we have to live into it.
I think this is a beautiful vision that most of us can get excited about.
But if we're honest, it hasn't fully trickled down to the way we handle our finances.
We still put way too much trust in money and we're afraid of what living more generously will do to our security.
Our head is in the kingdom, but our heart and our wallet is still under the sun.
And the solution that Jesus offers is not a fun one, but it's Jesus, so it's good.
He says, sell your possessions, give to the needy.
Provide yourselves with money bags that do not grow old, with a treasure in heaven that does not fail,
where no thief approaches and no moth destroys.
For where your treasure is, there your heart will be also.
Jesus says, if your head is in the kingdom and your heart is still under the sun, trust me and give it away.
Try it and see what happens.
He seems to be saying that you can actually move your heart by moving your money.
Like if you want to have a life of open-handed abundance, generosity, and yet you're still clinging tight to it.
He seems to say you can actually move your heart by moving your money.
It will begin slowly over time to reshape the way you view reality.
You will begin to see where true and abundant life is found.
So if you're in here and you don't yet know Jesus, I just ask you, is it possible that you've been believing a lie about what life is really all about?
Is it possible that life isn't actually just 60 to 80 years, 60 to 100 whatever years?
Is it possible that the God who made all of creation has actually created you to live for eternity?
And you can begin that process now.
I just invite you to consider that reality.
If that's something you want to talk to me about or somebody at the prayer team, we'd love to talk to you about that.
For those of you that have a good handle on your finances, take a look at your saving, your spending, and your generosity.
Ask yourself, what does this pattern reveal to me about where I'm putting my trust?
If you're in here and you've got no clue what's going on with your money, that's okay.
I've been there.
Believe me.
This is not a message of shame or guilt.
It's an invitation to begin to open your heart to God.
Be intentional.
Make a plan.
Work towards open-handed generosity.
It might be 10 years before you can give $1 to somebody because you've got so much need and deficit between what you have and what you can give.
That's okay.
Jesus is inviting you to an eternal process.
Jesus announces the kingdom of God.
The spirit of the Lord is upon me for he has anointed me to bring good news to the poor.
Just invite us to imagine a church that becomes a place that embodies this reality of God's kingdom to our community.
That we wouldn't just be a church that says the gospel is good news to the poor, but we would be a church that lives with open hands and demonstrates to people who are in need that don't yet know Jesus.
That this is a reality about his kingdom.
Imagine a church where we don't just pray, give us this day our daily bread, but we look for opportunities to provide daily bread for those around us who are in need.
My prayer for our church is that God would give us open eyes to see his kingdom more clearly and open hands to participate in his kingdom more freely.
Let's pray.
Father, we thank you.
For the one true son.
All of the inheritance is his.
And yet he did not count his place of equality with God as something to be grasped, but he stooped down.
Sacrificially laying down his life for you, for me, for us, so that we might freely inherit the abundance of God's kingdom.
At the right time, you saw us and you were Jehovah Jireh, the provider of our every need.
God, for those of us that are crippled with anxiety around our finances this morning, I pray that you would breathe on them peace.
God, I pray that you would get their eyes above their bank accounts and that as they walk out of this place, they would see your abundance all around them.
God, I pray that there would be people in their lives who know you or surrender to you that are prompted to meet their needs.
God, for those of us who have more than enough, and we have eyes to see, ears to hear, and hands to participate in your kingdom being good news to those who don't have what they need.
For your glory, for our good, and for the good of our neighbor.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.